Hello everybody. Today's דף daf is עין ב Ayin Bet 72. We
are officially two-thirds done with the מסכת masechet by the way.
And we're right in the middle of a very important הלכה למעשה
halacha l'maiseh discussion about if somebody does a שיתוף מבואות, shituf mevo'ot,
combining together the various courtyards in the street that they open into,
does that obviate the need for an עירוב חצרות? eruv chatzeirot? Or
alternatively, if the various courtyards do an עירוב eruv not just individually
but collectively, do they also need to do a שיתוף מבואות? shituf
mevo'ot? The basic difference is that an עירוב eruv is done with
bread, a שיתוף shituf can be done with anything. The גמרא Gemara
here discusses wine as an alternative. And
according to an עירוב eruv is put in a house in the
courtyard, a שיתוף shituf is put in the courtyard itself. The courtyard
to the מבוי mavoi is like the house to the courtyard. However,
רש"י Rashi says it could also be put in the house, but
it can be put in the courtyard. תוספות Tosafot says it can
only be put in the courtyard. And that's important for תוספות Tosafot
because otherwise how do you know if you're dealing with an עירוב
eruv not just of an individual courtyard but all the courtyards themselves
are getting together for an עירוב? eruv? How do you know whether
you call that עירוב eruv of all the courtyards, how do you
know whether you label it an
עירוב eruv or
שיתוף? shituf? So according to תוספות Tosafot there's always an indication based
on where it's placed. According to רש"י Rashi the answer is less
clear. Anyway, there's this debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you always
need both and the חכמים Chachamim say one can serve as a
substitute for the other. So we pick up, let's pick up again
from the bottom of עין א עמוד ב Ayin Aleph Amud Bet
the following debate. פליגי בה, Pligi bah, two lines from the bottom,
רב נחומי Rav Nechumi ורבא. v'Rava. רב נחומי Rav Nechumi and רבא
Rava debate this. חד אמר Chad amar בפת bepat דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דבחדא סגי. d'chulei alma lo pligi d'bachada sagi. If you use
bread for the שיתוף מבואות, shituf mevo'ot, you could have used wine,
you could have used anything. You chose to use bread and bread
works for an עירוב eruv of the courtyards, so therefore if you
actually use bread nobody would disagree דבחדא סגי d'bachada sagi one is
enough. It's enough to do the שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'ot because again
you actually signaled you're doing more by using bread. And number two
is it's something that would have worked for the עירוב. eruv. So
that certainly everybody agrees can be a substitute. כי פליגי, Ki pligi,
when did they debate? ביין. Beyayin. If you used wine for the
שיתוף, shituf, so you did your שיתוף shituf in wine which could
not have been done for the עירוב eruv but nevertheless does the
שיתוף shituf serve as a substitute for the עירוב? eruv? Top of
עין ב עמוד א. Ayin Bet Amud Aleph. וחד אמר, V'chad amar,
the other says, ביין דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דבעינא תרתי. beyayin d'chulei
alma lo pligi d'beina tartei. No, it's the opposite. I agree on
the hierarchy: bread is better than wine, but it works this way:
wine, even the rabbis would say wine of a שיתוף shituf cannot
be a substitute, a שיתוף shituf made with wine cannot be a
substitute for the עירוב. eruv. כי פליגי, Ki pligi, the debate is
בפת, bepat, with bread. And there the rabbis say bread if you
use it for the שיתוף shituf works and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says I'm sorry I always need both. And actually interestingly the reason
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said the גמרא Gemara said yesterday is
not some conceptual reason but more of a secondary concern that people
should not forget about the other institution of עירוב eruv if you
always are able to just do a שיתוף. shituf. Okay, so מתיב,
Mesiv, I ask you to see which way it goes, what their
debate is about. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, או מערבין או
משתתפין. o meiarvin o mishtatfin. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you have
to do both and the חכמים Chachamim say you can do one
or the other. מאי לאו, Mai lav, או מערבין בחצר בפת, o
meiarvin b'chatzer bepat, או משתתפין במבוי ביין? o mishtatfin b'mavoi beyayin?
Presumably that means you do either one according to its normal parameters.
Either you could do an עירוב eruv with bread of all the
courtyards together and it obviates the need of a שיתוף, shituf, or
you could do a שיתוף shituf with wine also of all the
courtyards together and it obviates the need for an עירוב. eruv. So
presumably though it says one or the other meaning each one according
to its normal parameters. So, which seems that they're debating the case
of wine, that even the wine case the rabbis say is okay
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, that one you need both.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Giddel amar Rav, הכי קאמר.
hachi ka'amar. No, no, we can read it otherwise. או מערבין בחצר
בפת o meiarvin b'chatzer bepat ומותרין כאן וכאן. u'mutarin kan v'kan.
Either you could do an עירוב eruv with the courtyard with bread
and then the courtyards will be able to, you can use one
courtyard to the next and you can also use the street, the
מבוי. mavoi. או משתתפין במבוי בפת ומותרין כאן וכאן, o mishtatfin b'mavoi
bepat u'mutarin kan v'kan,
or you could do a שיתוף shituf in the מבוי mavoi in
the shuks on the street with the bread and then you could
also individually use the courtyard. So basically, the answer is no, maybe
we're talking about you're using bread. Yes it said שיתוף shituf or
עירוב eruv and normally שיתוף shituf doesn't mean bread, but here maybe
it does mean bread. So it's not clear again whether they're debating
the case of wine or they're debating the case of bread. Now
we get to the key, the punchline, how do you פוסקין? paskin?
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, says רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב. Rav. Now remember this
is only אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda yesterday said we rule like רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So just one thing to be aware of is just that
we're about to give some פסקים, psakim, doesn't mean it's the unanimous
voice of the גמרא. Gemara. This is רב יהודה אמר רב. Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הלכה כרבי מאיר. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Meir. We rule like רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, you need both. ורב הונא אמר, V'Rav Huna amar, מנהג
כרבי מאיר. minhag k'Rabbi Meir. The practice is like רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. ורבי יוחנן אמר, V'Rabbi Yochanan amar, נהגו עם כרבי מאיר. nahagu
am k'Rabbi Meir. It's not that the custom... is but that's what
the people do. Now what's the difference? So first let me talk
about the difference between those three things and then talk about how
we actually פוסקין. pasken. So those three, that type of
a three levels came up earlier in the גמרא Gemara and you
might remember the difference is the following. הלכה halacha means that we
publicly say the פסק. psak. Everybody should know the הלכה halacha is
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you need both. מנהג כרבי מאיר minhag
k'Rabbi Meir means that that's an accepted position but we don't necessarily
go out of our way to correct people or to impose it
on people. If somebody comes and asks me the שאלה shaila I'll
say we rule like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But if I see
people that are doing otherwise and people that are saying you can
use the שיתוף shituf instead of the עירוב eiruv vice versa, I'm
not going to go out of my way to make a big
announcement. Oh everybody should know you have to go like רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. But I'll tell you that in a private פסק. psak.
נהגו nahagu is
the most low level. The נהגו nahagu doesn't mean that really we
don't even פוסקין pasken like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. People have adopted
that practice, but if you were to ask me the פסק psak
I would say no, you don't have to do both. But if
you're doing it already and you're acting like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
I'm not going to correct you. Okay, so נהגו nahagu really even
means the הלכה halacha is not like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but
that's what people are doing and I don't have to go out
of my way to correct them. Now the first thing I want
to say is, תוספות Tosafot says, but that's crazy. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is a חומרא. chumra. Why would I ever think that you
would have to go out of your way to correct somebody,
meaning there's a level lower than נהגו. nahagu. A level lower than
נהגו nahagu is people are doing it but has nothing to base
itself on and they have to be corrected. Nothing
like Judaism. So תוספות Tosafot says why do I have to say
who cares if people are doing רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? There's no
downside. Why would I ever think I might even
have to correct them? So תוספות Tosafot has two interesting downsides. Look
at the תוספות, Tosafot, the first wide line.
נהגו כרבי מאיר. nahagu k'Rabbi Meir. בפרק בתרא דתענית מפרש דארויה לא
אמרינן כוותיה B'perek Batra d'Taanit mifaresh d'aruyei lo amrina k'vantei we don't
rule like him, ואי עבדינן לא מחינן בידייהו v'i avdinan lo machinan
b'yadeihu if people do it we don't go out of our way
to stop them and correct them. So תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר
מה מחאה שייך כאן אם מחמירים כרבי מאיר. v'im tomar ma mecha'ah
shayach kan im machmirim k'Rabbi Meir. How would it ever even be
possible to think that I might want to correct them or stop
them if they're going like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? לעשות עירוב ושיתוף
la'asot eiruv v'shituf they're just being מחמיר machmir doing something else. So
ויש לומר v'yesh lomar he says two answers. One דלא הוי ברכה
לבטלה. d'lo havei bracha l'vatala. They're going to make a ברכה bracha
on the עירוב eiruv and on the שיתוף. shituf. So if you
don't have to do both you shouldn't be making a ברכה bracha
on the second one that you're doing. Right because you make a
ברכה bracha when you do the עירוב. eiruv. אי נמי i nami
he
says or אם נמנעים על כך להביא סכין וחמין לצורך מילה. im
nimna'im al kach l'havi sakin v'chamin l'tzorech mila. Right so remember cases
before we had you forgot to do an עירוב, eiruv, you forgot
to do a שיתוף, shituf, and the question was you need hot
water for the baby do you have to push off the ברית
מילה, bris mila, do you have to tell a non-Jew. So he
says if you think you need both there might be cases where
you're not going to be doing something you need to do because
you'll say oh I don't have both. This תוספות Tosafot is very
important because it just points out the truism that there's no such
thing as a pure חומרא. chumra. Every חומרא chumra has its קולות.
kulas. And if you're מחמיר machmir on this side you're going to
be מקיל meikel on that. If you're going to be מחמיר machmir
like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the הלכה halacha isn't really like
him, first of all you're going to be מקיל meikel you're going
to be doing ברכות לבטלה brachas l'vatala number one. And number two
you're going to be מקיל meikel because there's going to be circumstances
where you actually have a responsibility an obligation to carry there and
you're going to think because of a מצוה mitzvah or חולה choleh
whatever it is and you're going to think you can't do it
because you're being so frum and you think that you need both.
So it's actually a very valuable תוספות Tosafot to point out that
there's no such thing or there's almost never any such thing as
a unadulterated חומרא chumra and that no downside. There's always going to
be everything is going to be a trade-off in some other area.
And now by the way it's worth noting that here beside the
other than the ברכה לבטלה bracha l'vatala point the trade-off is normally
what the trade-off is. We're going to trade off בין אדם לחברו
bein adam l'chavero for the sake of בין אדם למקום. bein adam
l'makom. So we're not going to take care of the kid or
whatever although there also it's בין אדם למקום bein adam l'makom having
a ברית מילה בזמנו. bris mila bizmano. So that's number one just
to be aware of those types of trade-offs. Now how do we
פוסקין? pasken? So
here if you go the first way הלכה כרבי מאיר halacha k'Rabbi
Meir means we actually go ahead and we פוסקין pasken רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir then the key question is which version of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir יין או פת yayin o pat because okay if you
use wine maybe you say you can't do for the מבוי mavoi
what you can do for the מבוי mavoi doesn't substitute for the
עירוב eiruv and vice versa. But if you do פת pat at
least it should work. So there's a big debate in the ראשונים
rishonim whether we actually say that they're debating by wine or they're
debating by bread and many will say they're just debating by wine
like it sounded like.
כמה פת? kama pat?
So we haven't gotten up to that yet we're going to get
up to it but if you have two meals worth of bread
then it doesn't matter how many people are involved. So a box
of matzah clearly covers you for an entire city even a hundred
thousand people. Okay so we'll get to that but if there's a
certain thing that if there's a small number of people it's only
a small amount per person but once you hit two meals worth
then no matter how many people it's fine. So this is the
question what do you do so if they're only debating wine then
you use bread. you're actually okay. And you don't have to do
for every street and whatnot, you can just do one and it
works for all the courtyards and so on. So here actually is
a debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim. I'll just read you the שולחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch because you can guess what the answer is, since
when we make our own עירובס eruvs we don't do for every
separate street. So says here in שפ"ז Shin Peh Zayin in אורח
חיים, Orach Chaim, המשתתפין במבוי צריכין לערב בחצרות, Hamishtatfin bamavoi tzrichin le'arev
bechatzerot, if you do the מבוי mavoi you have to do the
courtyards, כדי שלא ישתכחו התינוקות תורת עירוב, kedei shelo yishtakechu hatinokot torat
eruv, like the רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's language, שאין התינוקות מכירין מה
נעשה במבוי she'ein hatinokot makirin mah na'aseh bamavoi because nobody pays attention
to what's going on in the מבוי. mavoi. They only pay attention
to the local streets or they don't realize that the מבוי mavoi
obviates the need for the streets and that there's an idea of
doing it in the streets, or the yards I should say, the
courtyards. לפיכך אם נשתתפו במבוי בפת סומכין עליו ואין צריכין לערב בחצרות.
Lefikach im nishtatfu bamavoi bepat somchin alav ve'ein tzrichin le'arev bechatzerot. So
if you use bread in the מבוי, mavoi, which is not your
normal thing to use in the מבוי, mavoi, so bread in the
מבוי mavoi does obviate the need for the עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzerot.
So that's why now when we make an עירוב eruv around the
whole city with the box of מצה, matzah, the rabbi takes one
box of מצה, matzah, he transfers ownership to the whole city, everybody
is partners in that box of matzah, you're unaware, but it's the
פת. pat. So therefore if you do it בפת bepat and you
do it for, you know, you can do it therefore for everything
and you don't need to do both an עירוב eruv and a
שיתוף. shituf. So that's actually how... I mean, who even knows...
I mean like how many... I have no idea he's doing it.
What do you mean? Half the time...
That's your problem all the time, Michael. But that's why it becomes
הלכה halacha and then you have to pay attention to how the
law is formulated.
So some שבת Shabbat when I forgot to buy bread, I can,
if I found out who actually keeps the box of מצה, matzah,
I could go get a couple of pieces of מצה matzah from
it.
Yes, you could. Okay.
So it was like the guy that went and picked up everybody's
liquor in
Israel to prove that
the non-Jew actually owned it.
Because even though normally... so Michael raised the point about הלכתא כדברי
המיקל, hilchata kedivrei hameikil, which is some of the arguments that the
ראשונים Rishonim use to say that at least we should assume that
they agree בפת, bepat, which is actually what we do. But then
again this proves that we might not universally say הלכתא כדברי המיקל
hilchata kedivrei hameikil because the last three statements in the גמרא Gemara
without really anybody being חולק cholek are all... so every now and
then like the גמרא Gemara pointed out yesterday we do like a
מחמיר machmir position. But even within there there's a push to say
at least we should say that they agree בפת, bepat, which is
what we actually do say. Okay.
So just between us and the people on the
YouTube, the box of מצה matzah was with Rabbi Winzer.
No it isn't. It's not. Okay. So now let's take a look
at the next משנה. mishnah.
חמשה חבורות. Chamishah chavurot. Now, so it's actually becoming very practical. First
we talked about how come you need, you can only do... you
know we could just do one box of מצה matzah and you
don't have to worry about every sort of courtyard or every street
by itself. And now we talk about,
about an apartment building. This is essentially what this next scenario is
going to be. So let's take a look, right? Is an apartment
building like one house and you don't need an עירוב eruv or
do you need an עירוב eruv in an apartment building? That would
be the question. You're in a city, you're in a city that
doesn't have an עירוב, eruv, so nobody... you're in a city that
doesn't have an עירוב. eruv. This is a very common scenario. Common?
Most places have an עירוב. eruv. But let's say anyway, you're in
a city that doesn't have an עירוב eruv and you're in an
apartment building. So you say okay it's an apartment building, it's all
within four walls, I can carry in the halls, I can carry
from my apartment to the next apartment. But that essentially is a
courtyard. Everybody's got their own individual little individual apartments. There's a shared
space, right? Do you need an עירוב eruv there? Or because you're
all in one building, it's basically defined
as one space. So that's the question. Do you need an עירוב
eruv in an apartment building? Let's take a look. חמשה חבורות
ששבתו בטרקלין אחד. Chamishah chavurot sheshavtu betraklin echad. Five groups of people,
could have just said five people but whatever. Five groups that all
spent שבת Shabbos in one like big castle, you know, one... one
hotel. Well, it's not a hotel but whatever. Anyway, one large building.
So five different groups in five different rooms.
בית שמאי אומרים עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה. Beit Shammai omrim eruv lechol
chavurah vechavurah. Each one has to participate in the עירוב. eruv. Each
one is a separate unit, has to participate in the עירוב. eruv.
Whether you want to carry in the common space of that castle
or whether you want to participate in the עירוב eruv of the
courtyard. By the way, רש"י Rashi points out that they also have
each one has an individual exit into the courtyard. Because if they
didn't have an individual exit into the courtyard, then that might be
different in terms of how many different participations do you need, right,
for the courtyard?
I mean it's the same case we've had before.
Right, or you mean one courtyard and five of the other ones
and so on. Yeah, it's a little different but it's the same
issue. So you know, if here's your big castle, right, and each
one has a separate room, but there's only one door into the
courtyard, right, and here's the courtyard, you know, so you might say
well you know there's effectively from the courtyard's perspective there's effectively only
one unit, right? So maybe it's different. Okay. But at least if
they wanted to use... yeah we're not going to talk about it
today. But if they wanted to use the common space, that at
least is like the courtyard to them, okay? But רש"י Rashi says
that the scenario here where they've got to, you know, where they
each, you know, where they each have to... what do you call
it? Where they each have to do an עירוב eruv even for
the courtyard itself, I don't know, I'll have to draw it something
like this, get my hands over it, but anyway, you know, it
would be a
case... if they each have their own exit into the courtyard, right,
then that's even more obvious that they're all separate units from the
courtyard's perspective. But even without that, they are certainly separate units in
terms of the common space and that's our apartment building scenario. Okay.
בית שמאי אומרים עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה, Beit Shammai omrim eruv lechol
chavurah vechavurah, each one needs to separately participate in the עירוב. eruv.
ובית הלל אומרים עירוב אחד לכולן, Uveit Hillel omrim eruv echad lechulan,
no, one is enough for everybody, which makes it sound like, oh
great, so you don't need an עירוב eruv in the apartment building.
But בית שמאי אומרים עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה, Beit Shammai omrim eruv
lechol chavurah vechavurah, you need an עירוב. eruv.
No, if they want one עירוב eruv if they want to participate,
thank you, one עירוב eruv if they want to participate in the
courtyard עירוב. eruv. But the reason one suffices, thank you, what they're
saying is if they want to participate in the courtyard, they only
need one. The reason one suffices is because internally they're seen as
one coherent unit. So therefore if they want to use the inner
space, they wouldn't need anything. Is that clear? Right, we're talking about
what they need to do to participate in the courtyard, which defines
how many units they are. And if they're one unit internally, therefore
they don't need to do an עירוב eruv for themselves, you know,
in the internal space.
What are you calling the courtyard? Like the lobby?
No, no, no, no, no, the outside, the חצר, chatzer, okay? Outside
the building. If they want to, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says each
need a separate one,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel says even for all these guys to
use the חצר, chatzer, right, and there are other buildings that also
open into the חצר, chatzer, right? So that's your normal עירוב eruv
scenario. So this is all one unit and they only need to
contribute one עירוב. eruv. So if they're all one unit, that means
to use this space, right, the hallway, right, you know, the common
space, they don't need an עירוב eruv because they're all one unit.
So that's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says. So it looks so
far that according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you would not need
an עירוב eruv in an apartment building. Let's keep on
going.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is saying you need
one for every person and every
unit to use a חצר? chatzer?
Yes, and then they'd have to do their own internal one. To
do the חצר chatzer each one has to contribute and to use
the internal one they'd all have to join together in an עירוב.
eruv. Okay.
ומודים בזמן שמקצתן שרויין בחדרים או בעליות, Umodim bizman shemiktsatan sheruyin bachadarim
o va'aliyot, but they agree that if they're actually in separate rooms
or some are in the, you know, upper story and some are
in the lower story, שצריכין עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה, shetsrichin eruv lechol
chavurah vechavurah, each one needs separate. So your question is, I thought
that's what we're talking about? I thought they were talking about that
they were in different sections, like different rooms. So what this is
signaling, and the גמרא's Gemara going to figure out the difference, is
that no, no, no, no, no, is that there's some degree of
division that even בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees makes them separate units.
And when בית הלל Beit Hillel says they're all one unit, that
means when the division between them is not absolute. So we're going
to see in the גמרא Gemara what that means about what type
of division בית הלל Beit Hillel says is not enough to separate
them. But it's clearly admitted there are some divisions that do fully
separate them, and that's our scenario just to jump to the punchline
about the apartment building. Apartment buildings for us is the last line
in the משנה. Mishnah. When they're in fully separate units, then they
are actually distinct and then if they want to use common space,
they have to make an עירוב. eruv. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara now tries to figure out where
is the debate and when would they agree that they're separate units.
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מחלוקת במסיפס. machloket bemespis.
The debate of are they separate units or one unit is when
it's a מסיפס, mespis, like a type of a low, you know,
flimsy barrier. אבל במחיצה עשרה, Aval bemechitza asara,
if they're really divided by a wall even if it's only ten
טפחים tefachim high, then you know, something that's a halachic wall barrier
that separates them, דברי הכל עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה, divrei hakol eruv
lechol chavurah vechavurah,
everybody agrees they're separate units. So that, you know, means that in
most cases בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
It's only when they're very like low-level barriers would that be their
debate that בית הלל Beit Hillel says they're all one. איכא דאמרי,
Ika de'amri, that's one version of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Some say
אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman אף במסיפס מחלוקת, af bemespis machloket,
that even by a low barrier is the debate and even by
a low barrier בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that they're separate and
בית הלל Beit Hillel says that they're one. Okay, but so that's
version number one, which is that, which is that, wait, wait, did
I get that right? Yeah, which is that if there's a, if
there's a מחיצה mechitza of ten טפחים, tefachim, everybody agrees they're separate
units. The question is when it's a low barrier. And
according to the first version, if there's a מחיצה mechitza ten טפחים,
tefachim, everybody agrees that they're separate units. The question is when it's
a low barrier. And according to the second version, they argue on
both cases. That בית הלל Beit Hillel says that whether it's a
low barrier or a מחיצה mechitza of ten טפחים, tefachim, they're one
unit, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai says in both cases they're separate
units. Okay, so according to the second version, אף במסיפס מחלוקת, af
bemespis machloket, they even debate a low barrier, but they also debate
the מחיצה. mechitza. So according to this version, it's not clear when,
at what stage would בית הלל Beit Hillel say it's really a
separate unit? But according to this version, בית הלל Beit Hillel would
say that even a מחיצה mechitza of ten טפחים tefachim remains one
unit. That's one version. Now we have another version of the debate.
פליגי Pligi בר bar רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya בר bar רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon בר bar רבי. Rebbe. חד אמר מחלוקת במחיצות המגיעות לתקרה.
Chad amar machlokes bemechitzot hamigi'ot letikra.
When does בית הלל Beis Hillel say that they are one unit
and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says separate, when the wall gets all
the way to the ceiling, אבל מחיצות שאינו מגיעות לתקרה, aval mechitzot
she'eino migiot letikra, if it doesn't get to the ceiling, the wall,
דברי הכל עירוב אחד לכולם, divrei hakol eruv echad lechulam, then even
there בית שמאי Beis Shammai would agree it's all together, it's all
one unit. וחד אמר, Vechad amar, the other says, מחלוקת במחיצות שאין
מגיעות לתקרה. machlokes bemechitzot she'ein migiot letikra. No, no, no. When it
doesn't get to the wall, that's the debate of one unit or
separate units. אבל מחיצות המגיעות לתקרה, aval mechitzot hamigiot letikra, if it
gets to the wall, דברי הכל צריכים עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה. divrei
hakol tzrichim eruv lechol chaburah vechaburah. Everybody agrees that you need a
separate. So this is getting a little confusing, but there are a
lot of scenarios, okay? Here's your case of your
נסתיס, nishtis, let's say your small little barrier. Here's your case of
your מחיצה. mechitzah. We'll draw your ceiling up here. Okay, there's your
case of your
מחיצה, mechitzah, well, make it a little bit less, that's עשרה טפחים.
asara tefachim. Here's your case of the thing that's אינה מגיעה לתקרה,
eina migia letikra, your wall, it's not exactly clear what makes that
better than the מחיצה mechitzah case, okay, לתקרה, letikra, and here's your
case of the wall that actually is מגיעות לתקרה. migios letikra. Now
the point is that if they debate the case of מגיעות לתקרה,
migios letikra, that even in that case בית הלל Beis Hillel says
you're one unit, what's
the case in the משנה Mishnah about separate rooms?
This is exactly fully separate rooms, the wall gets all the way
to the ceiling. So here there's a debate of רש"י Rashi ותוספות.
v'Tosafos. Maybe רש"י Rashi says מחיצות, mechitzos, or maybe תוספות. Tosafos. רש"י
Rashi says separate rooms in the משנה Mishnah means that actually they
were originally constructed as separate as opposed to here was constructed as
one big room and a wall got put up. תוספות Tosafos says
the difference is like Michael says, that even here we're still talking
about a מחיצה, mechitzah, some type of an ad hoc thing like
a curtain as opposed to a real wall, okay, if you have
a real wall and you have a really separate room, as sort
of signified by that, it originally was constructed that way and this
is a case of separate rooms, you know, separate rooms that everybody
agrees, okay, that everybody agrees and this is our apartment building, okay?
So in this case everybody says it's two groups, you know, okay,
and the question is, right, going all the way back to these
other things, where is the debate
that בית הלל Beis Hillel says this even בית שמאי Beis Shammai
בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees is two groups, okay? Is there any
place along this line this is even בית הלל Beis Hillel says
this? Is there any place along this line that בית שמאי Beis
Shammai would agree it's one group? Okay, so some say yeah, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai would agree here. Some say בית שמאי Beis Shammai
would agree here, won't agree here, you know what I'm saying, there's
a different question where along that line would בית שמאי Beis Shammai
say that it actually is considered one group and maybe בית הלל
Beis Hillel would even say it's considered two groups somewhere earlier on
this line. Maybe בית הלל Beis Hillel only says this is one
group, maybe this is already two groups. So we have many different
versions of where exactly is the debate, okay?
בית שמאי Beis Shammai sounds a little bit more מחמיר. machmir.
Yeah, he is being מחמיר machmir here, he considers them to be
two groups. Okay, so he's demanding more. Okay, so let's see what
the גמרא Gemara now says. Okay, מתיב, meisev, I'll ask you on
some of these various interpretations this is going to be a challenge
to.
אמר רב יהודה הסבור,
Amar Rav
Yehuda Hassavar, said רב יהודה הסבור, Rav Yehuda Hassavar, what's that name
הסבור? Hassavar? רש"י Rashi just says it means like סברא, sevara, like
he was very, sort of, you know, analytical. תוספות Tosafos says it
might be referring to his profession, some are connecting it or a
place, he has שבך, Savach, maybe it means a name place, or
that he was into making hats. Anyway, said this רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על מחיצות המגיעות לתקרה שצריכים
עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה. lo nechleku Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel al mechitzos
hamigiot letikra shetzrichim eruv lechol chaburah vechaburah. Everybody agrees once they get
to the wall that makes them separate groups. על מה נחלקו על
מחיצות שאין מגיעות לתקרה. al mah nechleku al mechitzos she'ein migiot letikra.
They debate when they don't get to the wall, שבית שמאי אומרים
עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה, sheBeis Shammai omrim eruv lechol chaburah vechaburah, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says that then they're separate groups, ובית הלל אומרים
עירוב אחד לכולם, u'Beis Hillel omrim eruv echad lechulam, no, if the
walls don't get to I said don't get to the wall, I
meant ceiling. If they all agree that if it gets to the
ceiling they're separate groups, they debate if it doesn't get to the
ceiling, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai then says that then they're separate
groups nevertheless and בית הלל Beis Hillel says that if it doesn't
get to the ceiling they're all going to be one group. So
the debate is by the... okay, this is the case, this is
the area of the debate, but according to this version, once it's
מגיעות לתקרה migios letikra even בית הלל Beis Hillel says that it
is two groups, okay, and the debate is שאינה מגיעות לתקרה she'eina
migios letikra and that's where they debate two groups or one group
in that scenario. Okay, so now let's see which of the different
various interpretations this is going to be a challenge
to. למאן דאמר במחיצות המגיעות לתקרה מחלוקת, Leman d'amar bemechitzos hamigiot letikra
machlokes, תיובתא. tiyufta. According to the version that even when it gets
to the wall, even when it gets to... I said it again,
even when it gets to the ceiling, even in that case בית
הלל Beis Hillel says it's one group, this is a contradiction because
this says when it gets to the ceiling everybody agrees it's separate
groups. ולמאן דאמר במחיצות שאין מגיעות לתקרה מחלוקת, U'leman d'amar bemechitzos she'ein
migiot letikra machlokes, סיעתא, siyata, it's a support because that's exactly what
he said, that when it gets to the ceiling... להאי לישנא דאמר
רב נחמן, L'hai lishna d'amar Rav Nachman, now according to
the
version where we're sort of working backwards of the four various various
variations we just said. להאי לישנא דאמר רב נחמן במסיפס מחלוקת, L'hai
lishna d'amar Rav Nachman bimispes machlokes, according to the debate that says
that they debate the מסיפס mispes case, right, that this is the
case they debate, but anything higher than that is two groups, it's
also a contradiction because here according to this version we're saying even
a real wall that's not מגיע לתקרה, magia latikra, according to בית
הלל Beis Hillel will say it's one and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says two. Okay, so according to the version that בית הלל Beis
Hillel said that even this case is one, that's obviously not that's
obviously a contradiction. According to the version that בית הלל Beis Hillel
said anything higher than this is two, it's also a contradiction because
here shows even once, you know even in this case בית הלל
Beis Hillel says that it is going to be one.
So להאי לישנא דאמר רב נחמן במסיפס מחלוקת, L'hai lishna d'amar Rav
Nachman bimispes machlokes, according to the version that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said that only a low barrier is the debate but anything higher,
a real מחיצה mechitza is going to be two, so that's תיובתא,
tyuvta, a contradiction, because here we're saying that even when as long
as it doesn't hit the ceiling, it's still considered one. להאי לישנא
דאמר רב נחמן אף במסיפס מחלוקת, L'hai lishna d'amar Rav Nachman af
bimispes machlokes, according to the version that רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
they debate both a low barrier and a מחיצה mechitza of ten,
לימא תהוי תיובתא, leima tehavi tyuvta, maybe it's a contradiction, because here
we see they debate even a big מחיצה mechitza that almost gets
up to the ceiling. So אמר לך רב נחמן, Amar lach Rav
Nachman, now רב נחמן Rav Nachman will say back to you פליגי
במחיצה והוא הדין במסיפס, pligi bimchitza vehu hadin bimispes, that they're debating
both, והא דקא מיפלגי במחיצה להודיעך כוחן דבית הלל. veha deka miflagi
bimchitza lehodiacha kochan deBeis Hillel. So what he says is like this,
he says according to the version that רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
they debate this, he says but I'm not saying they even debate
this, but they also debate the מחיצה mechitza case. So in both
of these cases בית הלל Beis Hillel says that it's one, it's
one group, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that it's two groups.
Okay, and if that's the way he's saying מחיצה mechitza is no
different than אינה מגעת לתקרה, eina magaas latikra, halachically it's ten טפחים,
tefachim, it doesn't reach the ceiling, so this really is all one
case. So if it's all one case, okay, he's saying I'm saying
they debate both. In both of those things בית הלל Beis Hillel
says it's one, it's one group, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
that it's two groups. Okay, so this version works for me. According
to the version that said that even when it reaches the wall
even there בית הלל Beis Hillel says one group, that's not true.
Here we're saying that that case בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees is
two groups. Okay, according to the version that anything higher than a
מסיפס mispes בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees it's two groups doesn't work
because here we're saying even in this case בית הלל Beis Hillel
says one group. But what we are saying is that the one
that said that the debate is by מסיפס mispes could say it's
even אף על גב דמסיפס, af al gav demispes, but it includes
this case and in both of these cases בית הלל Beis Hillel
says one group and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says two groups. Okay,
והא דקא מיפלגי במחיצה, veha deka miflagi bimchitza,
so when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says they're debating the מחיצה mechitza
that doesn't get up to the ceiling להודיעך כוחן דבית הלל lehodiacha
kochan deBeis Hillel to show you the strength of בית הלל Beis
Hillel that even in a very tall wall that just that almost
gets up to the ceiling, even there they say that it's one
group. וליפלוג במסיפס להודיעך כוחן דבית שמאי, Veliplug bimispes lehodiacha kochan deBeis
Shammai,
why not go to the other extreme and debate about a low
barrier to show you how מחמיר machmir בית שמאי Beis Shammai is,
that even a very low barrier בית שמאי Beis Shammai considers it
two groups? כוח דהיתרא עדיף, Koach deheteira adif, it's a bigger חידוש
chidush to show you how מקיל meikil you're willing to be. It's
always easy to be מחמיר, machmir, it's always easy to say yeah,
yeah, even a small thing, but to show that בית הלל Beis
Hillel is so מקיל meikil that even with this type of a
wall they consider it one group, that's the חידוש. chidush. Okay, so
we've got a ברייתא braisa that says that בית הלל Beis Hillel
and בית שמאי Beis Shammai disagree about the wall that doesn't reach
the ceiling. Once it reaches the ceiling, which is our case of
the apartment building, even a non-permanent wall or even one that was
done after the fact, בית הלל Beis Hillel says that it's going
to be two groups. Alright, so and the version that says that
they debate here is incorrect or whatever it's contradicted. Here once it
gets to the ceiling it's two groups. How about when it's very
low? בית שמאי Beis Shammai agree there or not? So we're saying
not necessarily, maybe they argue on both of these cases. בית שמאי
Beis Shammai will from this extreme to this extreme consider it to
be two groups and בית הלל Beis Hillel will always consider it
to be one group.
כדברי רבי יהודה סבר לה? Kidvrei Rabbi Yehuda savar lah?
Yes.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב, Amar
Rav Nachman amar Rav, now we get to discuss how we rule.
Okay. הלכה כרבי יהודה הסבא. Halacha keRabbi Yehuda Hasava.
Now it's obvious we rule like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. The question
is how do we rule in terms of interpreting the debate? So
we go like this ברייתא braisa that interprets the debate that even
בית הלל Beis Hillel only is talking when the מחיצה mechitza doesn't
get to the ceiling. Once it gets to the ceiling then you're
already two groups. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק מתניתין נמי דייקא, Amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak Masnisin nami dayka, this also can be sort
of inferred from a close read of the language of the משנה
mishna that this is the debate, that you know only until it
gets to the ceiling while it still hasn't gotten to the ceiling.
דקתני ומודים Dekatani umodim because בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees with בית
שמאי Beis Shammai that it's two groups בזמן שמקצתן שרויין בחדרים ובעליות
bizman shemiktzasan sheruyin bachadarim uba'aliyos שצריכים עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה. shetzrichim eiruv
lechol chabura vechabura.
When they're in different rooms or rooms and the second story, then
they are separate units and each one needs a separate עירוב. eiruv.
of to participate, you know, for the courtyard or an עירוב Eruv
for themselves if they want to carry in the common space. מאי
חדרים ומאי עליות, Mai chadarim u'mai aliyot, what makes them
special? אילימא חדרים חדרים ממש עליות עליות ממש, Ei'lima chadarim chadarim mamash
aliyot aliyot mamash, literally means separate rooms, פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious. Now
what's literally separate rooms? So again, Rashi says it means units that
were originally created as separate units. It didn't start with an open
space and then something erected in the middle, erected after. תוספות Tosafot
says it means real walls, not temporary walls. But anyway, if it's
a real separate unit, of course everybody agrees those are separate. אלא
לאו כעין חדרים כעין עליות, Ela lav ke'ein chadarim ke'ein aliyot, it
must mean like separate rooms, which is what? ומאי ניהו מחיצה המגעת
לתקרה, U'mai nihu mechitzah ha'maga'at la'tikrah, it's an after-the-fact מחיצה mechitzah that
was made. It wasn't originally made as a separate unit, or according
to תוספות Tosafot it's non-permanent, but it's similar to separate rooms because
it gets all the way to the ceiling. שמע מינה, Shma mina,
that is a good דיוק diyuk that if separate rooms are separate
then even anything that's a full wall will also be separate. So
according to this בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees to בית שמאי Beit
Shammai that if it is separate units, a literal wall that gets
all the way to the ceiling, that then they are separate and
therefore they might have to each individually participate in the עירוב Eruv
in the courtyard, but also if they want to use common space,
the hallways, they have, I mean that isn't being said, I'm inserting
all of that to make it relevant, we haven't discussed it but
that's sort of implicit, to make use the hallways they have to
also all create an עירוב Eruv amongst themselves, which means again if
you're in a city that has a doesn't have an עירוב, Eruv,
don't just assume you can carry in the apartment building. Now you
don't have to go knock on everybody's door, you can go ahead
and pick up a box of מצה matzah and say, you know,
I'm קונה koneh this for everybody in the apartment, in the building.
Problem is what about the non-Jewish people? So that does get to
an issue if there's time later I'll address it. Yes.
So what's interesting here is not בית
הלל'ס
Beit
Hillel's leniency,
it's בית הלל'ס Beit Hillel's stringency which proves the case we were
just talking about. Exactly, exactly. When does, I can't picture a scenario
where the leniency comes in, what situation are we talking about?
Then you'd have like
a room where
we'd have, you'd have like these low-level type of a thing. Yeah,
I mean, because that's I think, I think that's why the משנה
Mishnah says חמישה חבורות ששבתו בטרקלין. Chamishah chaburot she'shavtu b'traklin.
It doesn't just say you have people living in different apartment buil—
you know, rooms in an apartment building or in an inn, because
then of course you'd have full walls. But it imagines
that they all came to some common space, I mean, you know,
I mean I guess— the Astrodome? Yeah, that's exactly what I was
thinking of. You know, like when Katrina or whatever that they put
all these people into this huge gym or something like that and
they have some type of a barrier to give them quasi-privacy or
they you know some type of a you know of a what
do you call it
what are those called the those things they put up in office
those dividers or whatever partitions, you know, and they don't get up
to the תקרה. tikrah. That would be a scenario. Okay.
Let's say you're in a hospital in the room and there's like
a curtain thing.
Yeah, but that's מגעת לתקרה, maga'at la'tikrah, isn't it? No? No, that's
not מגעת לתקרה, maga'at la'tikrah, the curtain in the room in the
hospital?
No, the rod for
the curtain is high but then there's hooks. Yeah, exactly.
Anyway, to use the to use the hallways you need it, that's
clearly something, so somebody somebody's got to be, I mean if again
somebody's got to be responsible for taking care of the hospital issue,
right, of doing an עירוב Eruv for the hospital so people can
carry in there. Normal bungalow colonies also don't make an עירוב Eruv
like every bungalow is separate? Yeah, right, but that's more obvious, right,
that those are separate units.
What
about
the owners? I mean they don't individuals do not do—
Right, one somebody has to take responsibility. You know since you can
take a box of מצה matzah and do a קנין kinyan for
everybody in the in the yard they don't have to be aware
that they're doing it. The challenge is about the non-Jew case. So
let's read a little bit more and then I'll go back to
that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנא במה דברים
אמורים כשמוליכין את עירובן למקום אחר. Tana b'meh devarim amurim k'she'molichin et
eruvam le'makom acher. When are they debating whether, now again this is
I've given the point about carrying inside the space because it's more
relevant, but the גמרא Gemara here is focused on using the courtyard,
okay, going back to my old my case here that here's your
thing and here's the courtyard and you have these different exits or
whatever and they want to all share the courtyard. So there's other
people who are there's other people other houses who also want to
use the courtyard. Everybody has to participate. So this ברייתא braita is
going to distinguish are they considered one unit or multiple units based
on are they receiving the עירוב Eruv or contributing the עירוב? Eruv?
The more they're receiving it the more they can be seen as
like one coherent space, you know, and therefore they don't have to
participate. The rule is if the עירוב Eruv is put in your
house you don't have to participate. Okay, so let's take a look.
And I don't have
to divvy up my matzah. Right. במה דברים אמורים כשמוליכין את עירובן
למקום אחר, B'meh devarim amurim k'she'molichin et eruvam le'makom acher, when do
they have to each one give separately according to בית שמאי Beit
Shammai if you know even in lesser cases according to בית הלל
Beit Hillel when they're literally separate rooms when they're bringing their עירוב
Eruv somewhere
else? אבל אם היה עירובן בא אצלן דיהן עירוב אחד לכולן, Aval
im hayah eruvam ba etzlan dei'hen eruv echad le'kulan, everybody would say
one עירוב Eruv is enough because Because they're more of a coherent
of a unified unit. Let me read to the end and then
I'll tell you a little bit what רש״י Rashi says for insight
into this. כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, Ke-man azla ha detanya, who's it
going like that which we taught in the ברייתא? baraita? חמישה שגבו
את עירובן, Chamisha she-gaveu et eruvan, five people collected their
עירוב, eruv, meaning you have one courtyard which had five units. Everybody
made an עירוב eruv in that courtyard. Now courtyard A wants to
make a unified עירוב eruv with courtyard B. So כשהמוליכין את עירובן
למקום אחר keshe-molichin et eruvan le-makom acher when they bring their עירוב
eruv from A to B to unify those two courtyards, עירוב אחד
לכולן, eruv echad lekullan, it's enough for them to contribute one. So
the גמרא Gemara says כמאן כבית הלל. Ke-man Ke-Beit Hillel. That's like
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Now what does that mean? What that means
is the following is that the גמרא's Gemara understanding that when בית
הלל Beit Hillel said that here it's one, okay, and one is
enough, yes, it doesn't mean that
it's conceptually just one. It's basically like there were these separate units
in
here. It's basically call it three that became one. The fact that
they that it's a low wall whatever the case is it's a
מפספס, mifpas, okay, but they're still somewhat distinct. So it's parallel to
a case of three separate units in a courtyard that were combined
by an עירוב. eruv. There's an aspect which starts separate but then
there's something bringing them together. So that's the analogy it's making. These
units which is one is really three or five that became one.
Okay, and therefore so it's like you had people that made separate
units in a courtyard that made an עירוב. eruv. Now what's the
הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha there is that if courtyard A wants
to link with courtyard B because they're five that have become one
one person can represent the group and to bring the whole thing.
So בית הלל Beit Hillel says that's the same here. They've all
become one so one person can represent all of them and contribute
the loaf of bread to make the עירוב. eruv. He's representing the
group. But בית שמאי Beit Shammai says according to this that no
even in this case even though you've become one for yourself when
you want to link with another one everybody has to contribute separately.
And he would say the same thing here this is that's like
the case of the courtyard everybody has to contribute separately. The point
being that בית שמאי Beit Shammai is not saying that they are
fundamentally
completely separate units. He basically buys into בית הלל's Beit Hillel idea
that they are somewhat distinct but they've been unified. But nevertheless says
בית שמאי Beit Shammai when you want to contribute to others that
then you have to contribute separately. Okay so that's how the
גמרא Gemara is and he buys into בית הלל Beit Hillel but
then
you have to contribute separately because the גמרא Gemara says because the
גמרא Gemara says that the issue about a courtyard is only going
according to שיטת בית הלל shitat Beit Hillel which means that the
case of the house here of the טרקלין traksin is analogous to
the case of the courtyard which means that fundamentally there is something
that brings them together and nevertheless they debate how much you have
to contribute when you want to join another group. Okay so that's
the first version of saying it. That everybody agrees it's like they've
been they're somewhat distinct but they've been brought together and the debate
of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai is do
you have to contribute when you want separately or can you contribute
coherent as one unit when you contribute to another group. But when
you receive it here's the point even בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees
and this explains when you receive it then then even בית שמאי
Beit Shammai agrees that you are enough unified that you don't have
to give separately. Because when you receive you don't have to give
anyway. When you receive it's just receiving into the house that house
doesn't give so בית שמאי Beit Shammai according to this version agrees
that they are somewhat made into a group when they receive it's
fine the debate is when they give it do they then have
to be distinct or can they be one? Okay so איכא דאמרי
ikka de-amri others say במה דברים אמורים כשהיה עירובן אצלן bameh devarim
amurim keshe-haya eruvan etzlan no
that they really are debating whether they're a group or whether they're
distinct units. That even when the עירוב eruv comes to them בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says separate and בית הלל Beit Hillel says they're
a group. So even when it comes to them בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is saying I don't see them as a group I see
them as separate. אבל אם היו מוליכין את עירובן למקום אחר aval
im hayu molichin et eruvan le-makom acher but if they actually would
contribute their עירוב eruv elsewhere דברי הכל צריכין עירוב לכל חבורה וחבורה
divrei hakol tzrichin eruv le-chol chavurah va-chavurah
then even בית הלל Beit Hillel would agree that their being one
group doesn't help when they want to contribute. When they want to
contribute elsewhere each one becomes separate. So then the גמרא Gemara says
according to that כמאן אזלא הא דתניא חמישה שגבו את עירובן כשהמוליכין
את עירובן למקום אחר עירוב אחד לכולן ke-man azla ha detanya chamisha
she-gaveu et eruvan keshe-molichin et eruvan le-makom acher eruv echad lekullan that
when you had five houses in a courtyard that came together in
an עירוב eruv if they want to link with another
courtyard they don't have to give separately one can give for everyone
כמאן דלא כחד ke-man dela ke-chad that's like going like no one.
Because now we're saying that according to this version that
according to the version one everybody agreed they're separate units that became
a group and the debate is when that group contributes elsewhere בית
הלל Beit Hillel says one guy is enough and בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says separate. According to this version no בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says they're separate units בית הלל Beit Hillel is the only one
saying they're a group. So when you receive בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says that each one is separate and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
as long as you're receiving you're a group you don't have
to contribute. So if that's true, the idea that if a courtyard
wants to link with another, one person can represent the whole courtyard,
that's not even בית הלל, Beit Hillel, because according to this version,
even בית הלל Beit Hillel is saying that even though they're somewhat
of a group, they have to give separately. Okay, so that was
a little, a different issue being brought up, not just one unit
or separate, but does it matter if they give or if they
receive. Now, just to say a word about Michael's question about the
case of the apartment building.
So once you say that you need to do it, okay, it's
one thing if they're all Jewish and you do the box of
מצות, matzos, but what if there's non-Jews in the שכירות, sechirus, and
how do you manage that?
So, and that really should be the question you're asking about how
we do the עירוב eruv in the whole city. Part of that
answer is we do שכירות sechirus from the government and we say
that they have some right of eminent domain, and you know, somehow
say that that counts for everybody. But in terms of an apartment
building, it's usually easier because there's an idea which we saw something
like it before, called תפיסת יד. tfisas yad. You might remember before
there's a discussion about can the owner force you out of your
room and so on, you know, in terms of, in terms of
a case of rentals. So here, even if you cannot be forced
out of your building, you've got a lease, if the owner basically
owns the major appliances, you know, the, the, what do you call
it, like the stove or the refrigerator, then it's considered like he
is a, he unifies it all into one domain. So it's all
a single domain because he has a presence in each one of
the places. So that really substitutes for the עירוב eruv to unify
it. So then you don't even need an עירוב. eruv. But if
you rely on that, then you don't even do the box of
מצות. matzos.
Meaning even though there's a Jew and a non-Jew in the building?
Right.
So all rentals. It's all one domain. Now even if they're condos,
or if they're co-ops, I mean in my co-op, wait, we own
the stove, it came with the apartment. I think we do, I
think we do own it.
Yeah, it varies.
It varies from co-ops to condos.
The residents own the...
Yeah,
but
so that's a bigger challenge then. Yeah. I mean, the question is,
can city
doesn't have an עירוב eruv because we don't have an עירוב.
eruv. The interesting thing with a co-op is that I only own
shares,
and the shares entitle me to a certain size apartment. I don't
know what the rules are, like if the co-op board decided to
take me out of this one and give me another one that
was, you know, better, equal or better, would they be, they might
be legally entitled to, I don't know, because I only own shares,
I don't own a particular unit.
You actually own a piece of everybody's apartment.
Right. So co-op, condo is different. Even in a condo, right, the
question is like does the condominium association own like the stuff behind
the walls, right, don't they, like the wiring and all of that?
And the hallway and the common.
Well, the hallways doesn't help, they have to own something in the
individual unit in order, anyway, that's an idea of תפיסת יד tfisas
yad which works in a lot of those cases.
But that's only in a city that doesn't have an עירוב. eruv.
Right. If you have an עירוב, eruv, then however you do it
with all the other spaces by renting from the government, you sort
of do it for the inside.
But it's nice to have an apartment עירוב eruv for the weeks
that the עירוב eruv happens to be down.
That's true also.
What do they do in Boston, you know, wherever it is, you
know.
Right. Let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna. האחים שהיו
אוכלים על שלחן אביהם, Ha'achim shehayu ochlim al shulchan avihem,
brothers that were all sort of eating share on their father's table.
So you have different, you know, family has different houses in a
courtyard, but everybody gets together and eats at their father's house, you
know, their meals. They're still being supported by their father. וישנים בבתיהם,
Veshenim bevateihen, but they sleep in their individual homes. צריכים עירוב לכל
אחד ואחד. Tzrichim eruv lechol echad ve'echad. They're considered individual units, they're
not all considered one, you know, one ownership, and each one has
to contribute separately to the עירוב. eruv. ולפיכך, Ulefikach,
yeah, ולפיכך אם שכח אחד מהם ולא עירב, ulefikach im shachach echad
mehem velo eirev, מבטל את רשותו. mevatel es reshuson. So the obvious
consequence if one of the guys' brothers forgot and didn't make an
עירוב, eruv, he has to, you know, relinquish his rights in order
to let people use the courtyard. אימתי, Eimasai, when is this true?
בזמן שמוליכין עירובם במקום אחר. Bizman shemolichin eruvam bemakom acher. This might
sound familiar. When they go to contribute their עירוב eruv elsewhere, meaning
that the עירוב eruv is placed in somebody else's house outside of
the family, you know, there's a lot of other people in the
courtyard as well. אבל אם היה עירוב באצלן, Aval im hayah eruv
ba'etzlan, if they were the ones to receive the עירוב, eruv, או
שאין עמהם דיורין בחצר, o she'ein imahem diyurim bechatzer, nobody else is
living in the חצר, chatzer, אינם צריכים לערב, einam tzrichim le'arev, you
don't have to. So again the asymmetry that we saw at the
end of the discussion before that same like seemed like it came
out of nowhere, we're seeing that there is this issue of this
asymmetry, that they can be considered a coherent enough unit that if
they receive the, you know, the עירוב eruv from outside, so they're
one unit that received it. Or if nobody else is around, there
are no separate units. But when they're giving to others and they're
not just and they're more that more brings out their individual identity
and therefore each one has to contribute separately. So why that exactly
should be is not so clear, but that their more individuality is
becomes expressed when they are contributing rather than receiving.
And then even the guy who
forgot doesn't have to do ביטול? bitul? Right, if they're receiving. Or
if nobody else in the courtyard. Let's see the beginning of the
discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה
מקום לינה גורם, shema mina makom lina gorem, you see that because
we're considering them separate units, that it's not enough that they all
eat in one place. And this, as Michael said, is an important
halakhic question for various things. נר חנוכה, Ner Chanukah, other things, very
much comes up if people... guys are dorming at a ישיבה Yeshiva
and they have their separate rooms but they all eat in a
shared room. Do you define your place of domicile where you're eating
or where you're sleeping? So here they all eat at the father's
house but they sleep in their separate houses and it says that
they're separate units, at least for some aspects of the הלכה, halakha,
they're separate units. So you see what matters to define your domicile
is where you sleep. שמע מינה מקום לינה גורם. sh'ma mina makom
lina gorem. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav במקבלי פרס שנו. be-mikablei pras shanu. They
are receiving a portion, meaning when it says they're eating on their
father's table it was figurative. It means their father
sends them food from his house but they're all eating in their
own house. So you can't prove it from this משנה. mishna. Of
course if that was the case, the משנה mishna sounds like it's
exactly trying to make the point that it doesn't matter that they're
eating with their father. But the way the גמרא Gemara is reframing
it is no, maybe if they actually ate in their father's house
it would be
different. But there they're being fed by their father but they're eating
in their own houses. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, so we taught. מי
שיש לו בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת בחצר חבירו. mi she-yesh lo beit
sh'ar achsadra u-mirpeset be-chatzer chaveiro.
If you have various things which are not domiciles like a little
gatehouse or a porch in somebody else's courtyard, הרי זה אינו אוסר
עליו. harei zeh eino oser alav. Then even if you're sort of
camping out there for שבת, Shabbat, since it's not a structure that's
a domicile you do not make a problem you don't have to
participate in the עירוב. Eruv. בית התבן בית הבקר בית העצים ובית
האוצרות. beit ha-teven beit ha-bakar beit ha-etzim u-veit ha-otzarot. However if you
have a granary or a stable and so on, so that's considered
more of a place that has four walls and is fit for
domicile even though you're not exactly usually living there. הרי זה אוסר
עליו. harei zeh oser alav. That does create a problem. רבי יהודה
אומר אינו אוסר עליו אלא מקום דירה בלבד. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino
oser alav ela makom dira bilvad. No it has to be a
real place of domicile and not just something that's four walls and
a ceiling. So אמר רב יהודה amar Rav Yehuda מעשה בבן נפחא
שהיו לו חמש חצרות באושא. ma'aseh be-ven Napcha she-hayu lo chamesh chatzerot
be-Usha. This guy בן נפחא Ben Napcha had five courtyards in אושא,
Usha, meaning he had five different, he owned a piece of property
in five different
courtyards. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ואמרו אינו אוסר אלא בית דירה בלבד.
u-va ma'aseh lifnei chachamim ve-amru eino oser ela beit dira bilvad. That
it doesn't make a problem he doesn't have to participate in those
five עירוב eruvs because the property he has in those courtyards is
not a domicile. So the גמרא Gemara says בית דירה סלקא דעתך
אלא אימא
מקום דירה. beit dira salka daitach ela eima makom dira. So, and
we'll end there because that gets us back to the issue about
bread and sleeping. Okay so different questions about what considers to be
a domicile and then when we turn to tomorrow the issue is
going to be whether it emphasizes a place where you sleep or
a place where you eat, which gets back to the issue of
the משנה mishna of the different units in the father's
house.